hello and welcome everyone this is
active inference guest stream
84.1 on July 22nd
2024 on anthropocentric bias and the
possibility of artificial cognition with
rafhael M and Charles ratov so Raphael
and Charles thank you very much for
joining to you for introductions and to
take us through the paper and welcome
everyone this is stream 84 the YouTube
July 22nd
2024 thank you okay thank you guys go
for
it hi thanks for having us so I'm Rafael
I'm uh assant professor at MC University
in Australia Sydney in Charles
I'm Charles ratov I'm a permanent
research associate at the ulish research
center in ulish
Germany uh in a big Neuroscience
Institute so should we go through the
paper briefly so um so yeah we wrote
this paper uh together actually we
started by writing the general audience
piece that was published in bux online
um that was when was that few months ago
I guess yeah I think almost yeah close
to a year ago
maybe I don't think it was published a
year ago I think it was published in
202 2024 but yeah we we worked in for
while um yeah so this this piece um was
doing um I guess two things that piece
ofish in box he was pushing back against
what we call the All or Nothing
principle um which we Define as the idea
that either
um something has mind or it doesn't so
this kind of neat but uh overly
simplistic perhaps partition of things
into minded and non-m minded things and
we argue that this was uh not the best
framing to think of uh especially
unfamiliar systems that seem to have
sophisticated behavioral capacities like
large language models or AI systems in
general where we don't want to take
various cognitive capacities as a
package
and package them into this idea of a
mind where either you have the mind or
you haven't and if you have the mind you
have all of these things as a package
Consciousness reasoning uh Etc uh
planning memory um theory of Minds so we
thought so as a remedy to to this kind
of all and nothing approach we uh argued
for a more what we call a divide and
conquer strategy when studying the
cognitive capacities of of these systems
which involve um looking at these
capacities on a Pac me basis Case by
case with an open-minded empirical
approach um yeah child I know if you
have anything else that's on the V piece
of the
backgrounds yeah I mean we made one
point in there about um why it is that
people feel so torn
about reactions to large language models
and we said a little bit about the
psychology of essentialism
uh which is the idea
that um we naturally categorize
especially living things with respect to
a presumed Essence um so we gave an
example of an oak tree I think um and we
said that what people tend to think as
they grow up and learn about the natural
world is that uh an oak
tree remains an oak tree regardless of
uh changes to its observable
properties and um what makes it an oak
tree is this
unobservable essence of oak or whatever
that it presumably has and um there's
some experimental psychology and
developmental psychology showing that we
have a similar attitude towards
mindedness or having a mind uh and that
is a somewhat speculative explanation
for why the literature on large language
models is so torn and some people are
quite dismissive and other people think
that it's um a step away from
AGI uh it's that if
you
feel like you've got to put large
language models into one of two
boxes the box that you know has the
essence of mindedness or the box that
lacks it
then um you will be forced either to
say it doesn't have what it takes to do
any of the things that we associate with
having a mind such as reasoning or um it
has the essential characteristics of
mindedness and therefore we should
expect it to have all of the other
properties we associate with mindedness
as well such as Consciousness or
um understanding or
right I think it's worth yeah
emphasizing as you did that the the the
background motivation for starting to
write on this General piece in the first
place is indeed that the the general
discourse on AI systems and llms in
particular is extremely polarized in a
way that is that is very dichotomous and
Stark so you have on the one hand people
on one hand people um arguing that these
systems are no no more than um soal
stochastic parrots that are halfly
stitching together samples on the
training data and Regita them uh or that
there are no smart than toaster or that
you know they only do next token
prediction on export prediction and
therefore it is um uh a non-starter to
ascribe to them any form of cognitive
capacity or maybe even uh category
mistake uh and on the other hand of the
spectrum on the other end of the
spectrum you have people um arguing that
the systems hard D of superhuman
intelligence that they exhibit Sparks of
artificial general intelligence
to the or literally it's literally the
title of a of a paper by Microsoft
on4 um and many people hyping up the
capacity of the systems in a way that
might seem very speculative and unted
from actual empirical results so there
is this huge gap between these two
positions and there's person be a very
rich and complex Nuance middle ground
that is underexplored
um part partly perhaps I think we we did
make that point if not explicitly in the
published piece and in some draft that
um there's something reassuring about
being able to make definitive claims
about what these systems are and what
they do right so
either they're really unsophisticated or
they're really very much like us and uh
either of these claims kind of meet
somewhere in in a way
uh in saying that we we have a clear
idea of what the systems do and what
they are and I think it's a little more
epistemic and comfortable to say we we
have
to um study them empirically and find
out what they can or cannot do and why
uh and what are the underlying
mechanisms and we simply don't know a
priorize just by looking at the
architecture the the learning objective
the training data these sources of
evidence are insufficient to make the
definitive claims about what these
systems are capable of so I think that's
that was part of the a big part of the
motivation and that feeds into that uh
more um academic paper as
well yeah one other small side note
which we don't make in the paper but I
think might be relevant um especially
for people working in
philosophy uh llms are
epistemically uncomfortable I think that
was the phrase you just used ref which
is fitting um not only because they're
so new and different but also because
they are artifacts right they're things
that humans have constructed engineered
and
um we don't have a thorough
understanding of how they work I mean
mechanistic interpretability and various
behavioral uh research is helping us
improve our understanding but on the
whole our understanding is not nearly as
deep as hopefully it one day will
be and this is by itself a really
strange situation to be in that we've
constructed an artifact that we only
partially understand in the um in the
past artificial intelligence was seen as
um a way
of constructing something like an
epistemic assistant right something that
will help us but not something that will
kind of alienate us from the process of
coming to know about the world so I
think there's an extra layer of
discomfort um built
into thinking about large language
models and that may also play into the
[Music]
um the uh
divisiveness of debates about what they
can
do and and just to add to that um I
guess we should be clear that this does
not entail in any way that we think the
systems are so completely alien and
Beyond the rich of our current
understanding that anything goes and
that they could very well be uh you know
uh have like human-like intelligence or
superh human intelligence and we simply
cannot say whether or not they do or
because that's sometimes what you see in
some opets where people frame these
systems as novel alien forms of
intelligence that we have created but do
not understand or control and that is
you know is a slippery slope that leads
some people to then claim that they have
all these qu magical uh abilities and
that's not all what we want to say here
and in fact we want to resist that's a c
out yeah yeah yeah yeah so we we we
think that that's just as much of a cup
out as um
completely U dismissing a priori what
these systems might be capable of
without doing the work of looking into
the capacities with behavior and studies
so we very much want to resist both
extremes of the spectrum if that makes
sense okay so now should we move towards
the uh content of the current paper
sounds good yeah okay may maybe rapael I
just start with the distinction between
anthropomorphism and anthropocentrism
and then you can take the next step um
so everyone is aware of the problem of
anthropomorphic
bias in some form I mean
anthropomorphism is just the idea of
projecting human qualities onto
something
nonhuman and it's quite easy to
especially when you're having a
productive successful exchange with a
large language model um it's easy to
slip into this interpretive mode where
you reason about the responses of the
large language model uh as if they were
coming from an agent just like
you and
um maybe that's a useful thing to do in
some circumstances but uh from a
theoretical perspective it's certainly a
mistake because large language model is
uh radically unlike you know a human
agent in all sorts of ways but um that's
only one form of sort of human Centric
bias the other one is um
anthropocentrism or what we call them
Vox article anthropocentric
chauvinism and that idea is pretty
straightforward it's um the idea
that the human way of solving problems
is the gold standard of solving problems
generally so that to the extent that a
system solves a problem in a way that
diverges from the human
strategy it's uh only using a trick or a
fox solution
um it's uh it's not using a deep General
rational
strategy um and in the debate about what
large language models can
do we think that the
anthropomorphic bias is pretty well
recognized in the anthropocentric bias
is not so well recognized and so part of
this paper is is or
the main idea behind the paper is to um
present a systematic analysis of uh
anthropocentric bi how it comes about
and how to push back against
it right and and we we want to be very
clear and hopefully we're clearing the
paper that the reason why we focus on
anthropocentric bias here is just
because it is I think as Charles
mentioned less
um less discussed um and less recognized
or some forms of it l recognized and we
make we propose this new taxonomy um but
it's not at all to suggest that it's uh
more problematic or more important than
the anthropomorphic bias that's well
discussed in the literature of the
anthrop morphic biases plural um so in
other words this is not um you know to
to to frame things in in this slightly
problematic dichotomous way of thinking
that's common in the discourse on llm
this is not
a paper that is Ping to the llm booster
or llm hype Camp um even though it is
pushing back against a certain form of
dismissal of athentic biases that only
exclusively emphasizes theomorphic
biases um but perhaps we should flesh
this out a little bit already with the
first point we make here in the paper
about the performance competence
distinction which is a nice for to bring
about both anthropomorphism and
anthropocentrism regarding um ATMs so
this distinction uh is a very classic
distinction in linguistics and cognitive
science and it has already been applied
to AI systems the networks productively
like people like chess Farson um so
there's nothing really new here but the
distinction comes from no chumsky
originally and the idea is that um
performance pertains to the external
behavior of a system um in a particular
domain and uh competence is the kind of
set of underlying knowledge and
computations U or mechanisms that uh
enable the system to achieve that
behavior um and a familiar observation
in in linguistics Linguistics and
cognitive science is that there is a
double dissociation between performance
and competence so if you take uh for
example um
language um I might during this very
podcast make some grammatic
mistakes or some other mistakes in fact
I've already um misspoken a few times I
think and repeated myself so I've made
performance errors um but this does not
entail necessarily hopefully that I'm an
incompetent language user and that I
don't have the line linguistic
competence
um so that's a well recognized
dissociation you can be competent and
yet make some errors um and the reason
for that is that there might be some
additional factors that are unrelated to
the underly competence that might impede
on my performance so for example I might
be distracted when I speak or there
might be other um effects uh on my
speaking performance that don't actually
originate from a lack of competence but
just impede on my on on the the the the
idealized expression external
manifestation of my competence and this
is why I miss speak but it's also what
recognize that you can have good
performance without competence so we
give here the example of a student
chating on a test or memorizing Test
Answers by brute forcing U the test it's
a slightly more um I guess gray area but
at least in the cheating case a student
can a a test without being competent in
whatever the test is actually testing
for um and it's also well acknowledged
in cognitive science that they can do
instances like this
throughout
um you know
um like that that can be manifest
certain experimental settings where the
test subject is right for the wrong
reasons as it were NE is doing well it's
exhibiting good performance and then we
realize the underlying reason for good
performance is that there was some
perhaps some curis stic that the
experimenters or the scientists having
thought about that could for this good
performance but but doesn't actually
amount to whatever competence that we're
setting out to test um so we we start by
saying well this is what we recognize in
linguistics this is the association that
suppli to humans across the board you
can have performance without competence
good performance without competence and
you can have bad performance despite
competence now when it comes to llms the
point we make just going to scroll as we
go um we have some figures to sh later
but the point we make is that um
generally people stress the dissociation
apply the distinction to LMS but stress
the sociation only in One Direction
unlike in the case of human where it's
bidirectional and so what people do
generally is to say well LMS famously
you know if you look at the gp4
technical report and and various
other any any any report about a new
stateof the LM uh they are getting
really really good
add a number of tests and number of
benchmarks and even um human exam
examinations human exams uh the bar exam
medical exams Etc so they can they
really good performance uh tests that we
tend to think are really difficult tests
that one can only uh pass at least a
human could only pass if they have a
really significant non amount of
competence in C domain um and the point
that is made when it comes to lmis be
careful slow down and try to find out
why the model is doing well on that test
because there are various reason why it
could do well that do not actually
indicate that the model has the
underlying competence that a test was
designed for when it comes to humans so
one big concern for example is data
contamination where very large language
models TR internal scale
data
um uh can easily be trained on some test
items from common benchmarks that leak
into the training data such that they
can then do really well on the on the on
the Benchmark just because they've
essentially memorized um test items and
there are other more subtle um more
subtle reasons why um performance could
be very good for the wrong reasons so
that's very well recognized and a lot of
the people who push back against
anthropomorphic bias when it comes to LM
make that point careful do not take onic
attitude to the systems the reason why
they do well is not because they have
human like intelligence or human like
cognitive capacities but it's for this
trivial contingent or um you know
otherwise relevant reasons um that accom
for the good performance now when it
comes to the other dissociation ofation
the other direction their people are
very reluctant to apply to
LMS and we think it's because it's
essentially people think in a human case
you can make sense of the idea that a
human could do badly on a test or could
perform badly on a task and yet have the
competence that you're trying to test
but there might be some auxiliary
factors such as um working memory
limitations um attention deficits Etc
that could imped on the performance but
in the language model I I
think we what what we argue in the in
the paper we want to argue in the longer
version of the paper is that um people
don't a lot of people don't think that
there is an
analogous um mechanism at play where
there could be some kind of oxil factor
that impedes on performance performance
is what you get what you see is what you
get and and and so the performance is a
direct manifestation of
um what the system is computing if if
performance if if you have performance
errors that can only be explained by the
lack of competence because there is no
additional
um uh
independent factor or module that could
impede on the performance sources of
interference you might say yeah great
yeah um so yeah I mean I'll I'll um pass
it over to you Charles I just wanted to
to set up the this distinction
yeah yeah
um right so I mean if you think about
a
traditional uh computer
program at least if you think about a
simple computer
program it's odd to think of it as some
sort of complex systems where complex
system where one part of it could sort
of interfere with the workings of
another part of it but um one of the
points we want to make is that um
something like that
is a
realistic um possibility with large
language models um okay but I I suppose
the next part of the paper goes into a
taxonomy of anthropocentric bias and the
first sort of
overarching point is the distinction
between type one and type two so the
type one
anthropocentrism is a tendency to assume
that lm's performance failures um
designed to measure
competence um always indicates that it
lacks uh that competence and so
we I before we so we'll say something
about three different kinds of type one
anthropocentric bias but first a a
background Point um which is
that
um whenever we think it's possible to
give a mechan istic explanation of some
complicated
phenomenon we always have to forground
some factors some
variables uh and background
others and
um
the properties that
we push into the
background
um nevertheless matter we're still
making assumptions about the nature of
those properties when we try to
articulate what's going on with the
other properties that we're paying more
attention to and if assumptions about
those properties in the background turn
out to be wrong then those mistakes will
um corrupt our
explanation that attends only to the
foregrounded factor so that's a little
bit abstract let me just give you a
simple example
um in comparative cognition one famous
uh behavioral experiment is the mirror
test for
self-recognition so the question is
roughly um do non-human animals have
something like uh a
concept of
self and the strategy is to um put some
sort of Mark on their body uh and the
original experiments it was a Red Dot on
the forehead of uh maybe a monkey and or
a bird or whatever and then
um you put that animal in front of a
mirror and see if it um makes any
attempt to get rid of the mark and if it
does make an attempt to get rid of the
mark that shows that it recognizes that
the image in the mirror is an image of
itself and otherwise
not um so that that's a
a cool way to get it a really difficult
and Abstract question about the mind of
a non-human animal but it presumes or it
assumes that animals will care about the
fact that they have a red dot on their
forehead that they will be bothered by
that and be motivated to get rid of it
and if that assumption is wrong then
they might fail the mirror test for
self-recognition um for reasons that
have little to do with the presence or
absence of a capacity for
self-recognition and so something
similar to that is going on uh we say in
large language models um so the first uh
example that we give is to do with task
demands so uh you
can it's it's a pretty natural uh idea
that when Whenever you set up a
behavioral
task um there will be demands associated
with that task that are not directly
related to the capacity that you're
trying to test so to take the most
obvious example that I can think of if
you give someone a written test they
have to be able to write they have to
you know have a hand and a pen and
whatever uh and um if their you know
hand uh was injured or whatever and they
couldn't write then um their failure to
fill out the test wouldn't tell you
anything about their uh you know
academic
knowledge um so we suggest that there
are auxiliary task
demands uh
in behavioral tests of a large language
model and they're subtle um you wouldn't
you wouldn't think of this right away
but um we talk about a paper from uh who
and Frank uh they have a couple papers
on on this topic but what they do is
they give a large language model um the
following sort of question uh this is a
question it's for a grammaticality
judgment so you can see on the image
there which sentence is better in
English number one every child has
studied number two every child have
studied uh answer with one or two and it
gives uh the wrong
output um but then
you can also simply look at the
probabilities assigned to each of those
sentences within the model and uh figure
out directly whether the model thinks
that input a is more likely than input B
and it turns out that on a wide variety
of questions of this kind um the direct
comparison uh does or the large language
models perform better with the direct
comparison than they do with the more
complex demand
for uh metalinguistic judgment so the
fact that the model has to process the
numbering of the uh options and then
answer in terms of a number uh
is a subtle but
nevertheless um
important additional variable in the
experiment and that can influence the
model's capacity to get the answer
right Rafel do you want to add to
that no I think that well maybe we can
mention briefly the theorder example we
discuss which is from um this paper by
Andre Lan um which which kind
of um has a little extra ingredient that
makes the example interesting and even
more problem in terms of comparative
psychology which is um one way in which
auxiliary Tas demands can be ignored or
um disregarded or uh overlooked is when
uh you are doing a direct comparision
between humans and LMS on a task and the
experimental conditions are mismatched
in such a way that the task as you set
up imp the stronger demands stronger
task auxilary demands on the LM than it
does on human subjects that's something
that that can happen quite often and so
there is this this interesting example
from a couple of papers originally
published by black rights and colleagues
from Stand the H group where they looked
at um the ability of language models to
handle
recursion um looking at Center B it
closes uh how such
closes might
um for example when you add a
prepositional phrase with the subject of
the sentence and the verb might throw
off either humans or llms into
agreeing the the verb in the wrong way
so giving the wrong number to the verb
um for example the
keys that the man put on the table
here it should be R because Keys is
plural but because you have cloes in the
middle uh and if you add more closes
like this that un bedded in the middle
people and alms can get confused and and
U predict that the verb should be EAS
for example so um they tested this on
humans nms and found that on the more
complex examples involving complex more
complex constructions or recursion um
humans were doing decently well but
performance was collapsing compared to
the simpler examples and and from Deep
Mind um looked into that and realized
that the experimental conditions were
mismatched so the humans as is very
common in in ctive science experiments
were getting some training before they
completed the test items to just get
familiarized with the task so they they
were given some examples of the task um
for each condition and the LM were just
prompted zero shot as um people usually
put it so just um without any example
just on blank and uh Andrew found out
that if you he he he replicated the
experiments but added some proper
matched uh testing conditions for the LM
um so adding some examples of the task
in the prompt what it's known as F shot
prompting and with that he found that
performance was equivalent in in fact
the LM that he tested was slightly
better on a more complex constructions
than humans so when you match the test
conditions here you actually match also
I you it's it's not it's not automatic
but you you you can match the test
demands I mean it could be that there
are reasons why the very same
experimental conditions would result in
different demands for humans and other
but you still in this case even out the
playing Ground playing field uh in such
a way that you don't find the behavioral
discrepancy that you found ini
any um
yeah um good so shall we continue to the
next yeah section
um so another
uh another way that auxiliary or another
type of auxiliary task demand is input
independent computational limitations um
and here we're thinking of a few papers
that show that the number of forward
passes that a Transformer can make uh
influences its ability to find the right
spot in parameter space so you neural
networks
are um function
approximators uh but
they
um their ability to approximate a
function can can be eliminated uh can be
limited by the
um the the number of computations it's
allowed to
reform and
um
the sort of crucial feature of uh
Transformers in this example is that um
the number of
operations that determines the next
token is limited by the number number of
tokens that it's seen so
far um and it turns out that um if you
train a
Transformer with um additional
meaningless
tokens
um like pause tokens like the word pause
uh you
can increase its accuracy across a range
of of question typ
um
and yeah this
is this counts as an auxiliary task
demand in our view because um it's doing
something roughly analogous to sort of
giving the model that's demanded
auxilary Factor right but not yeah yeah
sorry I'll yeah um it's it's doing
something like giving the model uh time
to think and
um yeah so so you might think that the
absence of that additional inference
time is uh a
factor that is not directly not
conceptually related to its capacity to
answer uh a question like the one on the
screen um you know a simple arithmetical
question uh ref do you want to fill in
more yeah yeah no so so I think that
analogy is a nice one time to think
because if you if you tested a human on
even simple mathematical questions or
any any task really and just as them you
know tell them they have like one second
to just blur out an answer performance
would probably be pretty bad um and you
can think of asking an llm to answer a
question point blank as very very loely
analogous to that obviously this is an
analogy and there are very important
differences here but I think it's a
helpful heuristic to think about what is
um what is going on roughly here namely
uh in in above cases the system the
human of the llm does not get the chance
to perform the necessary computations to
derive the correct answer and so yeah
what we talk about in the paper is that
you have this experimental work showing
that if you ask a question to language
model um the amount of tokens it's a
it's it's allowed to generate before
providing the
answer um makes a difference to how
accurate it is so if if uh it just
generates a few tokens then have to give
an answer or even if it just has to give
the answer point blank with the very
first token it's going to be less
accurate that if you give it a chance to
generate a number of tokens before giv
the answer so the usual way in which
this is understood is that when you ask
when you you you allow the LM to
generate a number of tokens before
getting the answer or you even prompted
to do so you say think step by step for
example um that's known as Chain of
Thought prompting and essentially what
you're doing is you're forcing the llm
to generate a reasoning Trace what looks
outwardly externally like a reasoning
Trace in the output before giving an
answer and we know CH of thought
prompting increases performance accuracy
um but what was found by a couple of
papers um is that the uh mechanistic
influence of this process is not
entirely due to the nature of the tokens
that are generated in this reasoning
Trace in other words it's not just that
the llm has
to um generate the right tokens
corresponding to different steps of
reasoning before giving an answer
in fact the very fact that you allow the
llm to just generate tokens any token
before giving an answer from a
mechanistic perspective affords the
system to perform additional
computations that can complete a
competitional circuit that otherwise
wouldn't get a chance to be completed
and to derive the correct answer so as
Charles mentioned you can have you can
set up an experiment when you have the
llm just generate meaningless tokens
like Lal just dots a bunch of dots dot
tokens before giving the answer and the
more dots you allow before the token
gives the answer the greater the
expressivity of the system and the more
um the more kinds of problem problems
you can answer um and so as Charles
mentioned every time an LM is generating
a token the LM is performing one forward
pass um and so the more tokens it's
generating the more forward presses it's
doing and one way to think about what's
going on here as well is that having
these additional forward passes where
you you fit back the whole input
sequence plus the previously generated
tokens into the system to generate the
next is also a way to introduce the form
of recurrence in Transformers that are
not in terms of the architecture
recurrent networks um so that increases
the facility and uh you know in
complexity theic terms and uh yeah there
is there is pretty compil evidence that
um if you don't allow for that then
you're imposing a limitation that again
we think is very very Loosely analogous
to prompting a human to Point Long
question without thinking um so that's
an S an auxiliary Factor because if you
give the LM the opportunity to generate
enough tokens um it might have the
competence to um solve a task but you
might not see that otherwise and you
might get from errors that you to think
it's
compid yeah okay um so the the third
type of type one
anthropocentric U bias that we talk
about is mechanistic interference and so
um this comes from the mechanistic
interpretability work and the basic idea
is that because um large language models
are capable of in context learning they
can uh learn different strategies for
solving a different particular type of
problem and the strategy that they
Implement at a given time can be
different so um you can talk about this
in terms of uh virtual circuits that are
formed inside the language
model and um there's some interesting
work from uh Neil Nanda and others uh
showing that in some
circumstances uh these two circuits can
compete with one another
um so at a certain level of uh or after
a certain amount of training um you get
one circuit operative after a bit more
training you have two different circuits
um but they're uh the first circuit is
still sort of dominant and um then after
additional training the model um
converges on on the second circuit and
uh the first one uh slowly gets um sort
of it sort of ceases to influence the
internal operations of the model and
it's only once you reach that third uh
phase uh at which the
um
the benefits of the second circuit with
respect to the first become
visible so you can you can show using
decoding work that the second circuit is
there uh before you can show
behaviorally that the second circuit uh
yields better performance accuracy on on
the task so um I I suppose there's a
combination of two ideas here one is
that um
there are different strategies a model
can Implement for solving a
problem we
can detect those
strategies internally using decoding
methods um so three ideas and then the
third is
uh a good
strategy can
be uh present in some sense in the model
um before it has had the chance to
influence
behavior um and and so this is just
another way that the link between
performance and competence is shown to
be complicated than it might seem at
first raap can certainly
exp and um yeah just to to clarify one
thing so the circuits are just um you
know to think about the caal structure
of new network and essentially
computational subgraphs of the network
that have a specific function you can
think of a circuit as implementing a
particular algorithm or set of
computations um and so part of what
people are interested in in this
mechanistic inter literature that we
build on people like neiland Chola and
others is reverse engineering the
circuits that in deep networks and large
language models um peer to implement
certain well well defined algorithms in
some cases at least um and the emerging
picture that we build on here is that um
there is a lot of redundancy built into
neuron networks as they learn to U
perform a task optimizes function that
in many cases translate into redundant
circuits that relate to the same tasks
the same kinds of um the same kinds of
input output mappings and uh for these
circuits might be somewhat identical
circuits that are just redundant or they
might be different algorithm to to to do
similar thing and different strategies
to solve some problem as where maybe one
will be a bit more approximative and the
other one a bit more exact more
computationally intensive so that's
where you can have some uh
interference um where one um or at Le
some competition where one circuit takes
over another and um
such that the other becomes kind of you
know it's it's there it's latent in the
system but doesn't get a chance to
inflence behavior on a specific input so
you can get a performance error for that
reason and this can combine with the
other things we mentioned here so things
like Tas
demands the first thing we discussed as
well as the number of tokens you
generate both of these things could
cause a particle of circuit to take over
another um so it's it's we can think of
this holistically
um perhaps if you ask a question point
blank to a model without letting it
generate a bunch of tokens before
getting an answer then one particular
approximate circuit might take over that
gives the wrong answer if you let it
generate more tokens then another morea
circuit might be given a chance to um in
C inflence the output reasing in the
right answer and similarly we task
demands uh strong task demands might uh
in some cases
um impede on the uh triggering of a
certain circuit that would otherwise
have given the right answer um so that
could be the case perhaps in the LCR and
linan example where giving examples of
the task in the PRS might actually Prime
the right circuit to solve the task
about complex recursive cases in the
right way um so yeah these are the three
main auxiliary factors that would relate
to
what we call type one anthropomorphism
anism sorry I guess we should we been
AIT long already so we should be quick
on type two do you want to briefly
explain type two child yeah so type type
one uh deals with cases where
performance of the model
is um weak compared to humans so the
model doesn't do so well um and then
type two is when the model does do well
but nevertheless is different in some
respect from the
uh performance profile of the human or
we have some evidence to think that the
model uses a different strategy than
humans typically use and um the idea is
that um even once you hold performance
equivalent or average performance
equivalent um you know making a
different pattern of errors or adopting
a different strategy as evidenced by uh
you know some interpretability work any
deviance from the human strategy is
evidence of
fragility or only uh a trick
solution
um and
uh this point is a bit more
philosophical I suppose but the um idea
is
that the human strategy for solving a
problem um
isn't necessarily the most General
strategy for solving a problem and uh
what matters is whether the
strategy that is pursued by the model is
General whether it's robust whether it's
accurate uh and not merely whether it
mirrors the human
strategy um yeah and we we we end the we
end the behavior by considering an
objection um which is
um why
um
like given that um in humans we study
cognition largely through
language um and given that LMS are
trained on language or on linguistic
outputs from
humans um isn't it appropriate after
role to treat um human cognition as the
correct or appropriate thetic to study
LMS and we to that we answer that it
depends how we think of of of that
dialectic um so we acknowledge that
there is there is
no really other option than to start our
investigation of cognitive abilities in
llms by with reference to human
cognitive abilities using human
cognitive abilities as some kind of real
reference points things like FY of Mind
memory
metacognition R forms of reasoning Etc
that are familiar to us because we
humans have them um and this is the same
thing by the way in animal cognition for
example or in developmental psychology
where in any comparative psychology
setup um the reference point for what
concept psychological capacities
initially at least um is is necessarily
tied up with our conception of what we
human we humans have in our repertoire
of capacities but we emphasize that this
is only the starting point so here we B
ter from the philosopher Ali Bo who
calls this investigative kinds
investigative cognitive kinds we start
with a cognitive kind like memory or
metacognition tic memory met the of mind
um as as an investigative starting point
the starting point to the investigation
and then we have we we can try start
operational operationalizing this
concept this kind this cognitive
capacity in an experiment testing LMS on
it with an open manded empirical
approach and then based on the results
from that iteratively
refine the capacities that we are T the
capacity that we're targeting or
definition of the capacity we're
targeting in a way that could Gra ually
lead us to shed the the initial
anthropocentric assumptions that we have
such that as the
experimental um project runs a COR or as
as uh we make we get more results and
and refine our Concepts we may end up
with
um something that no longer looks like
looking trying to find human litic
memory in Ravens or uh in um
or in
LMS but ends up looking like looking for
something that some capacity that is
that shares some similarity with human
human episodic memory but is different
in other
respects um and so we can gradually come
up with a kind of cognitive ontology for
the systems that is less
anthropocentric um so we emphasize that
this is kind of dous feedback look here
that's that's that premise on
open-minded empirical investigation that
doesn't settle this questions a priori
but has to start as a necessary starting
point with the the reference to human
cognition I don't know if you want to
add to that
J um no I think that's pretty good maybe
we should uh move on to
questions yeah sound
good
awesome wow you should stop sharing my
screen uh you you can stop sharing or
you could leave it up but I can move it
awesome
okay yeah a lot of interesting uh pieces
there so thank you I'll read some
questions from the live chat but first I
just wanted to read a short quote from
the
2022 active inference textbook they
wrote um on page 195 some decades ago
the philosopher dennit lamented that
cognitive science scientists devote too
much effort to modeling isolated
subsystems EG perception language
understanding whose boundaries are often
arbitrary he suggested to try modeling
the whole iguana a complete cognitive
creature perhaps a simple one and
environmental Niche for it to cope with
so it's interesting about the approach
that you're taking this is kind of a
simple synthetic
iguana but that's leading to to to the
the bringing to Bear of a lot of these
empirical phenomena because there is
something and and and so I saw in the
presentation paper kind of this call for
like deliberate investigation rather
than just chopping up the Iguana a
priori with a framework that that
applies to humans or that centers humans
or or that just uh soothes the epistemic
challenge that's presented
okay okay first question from Dave he
wrote have you looked at Daniel
dennett's distinction between competence
without awareness and competence with
awareness he expands on this in the 2023
from bacteria to B and back I find this
much more valuable than chomsky's highly
problematic performance without
competence a situation that chsky posits
but doesn't look at
deeply where do you put awareness in all
of this
competency
uh well maybe I'll let you take uh that
one in a second CH because you're you're
maybe morean than than I am but I'll
just say um awareness is a very Pocus
term like many terms uh in philosophy L
but particularly this one more than many
others I think so um it can mean lot of
different things all different contexts
um here we don't focus on things like
Consciousness because I think we
probably both agree that it's a less
tractable uh maybe empirical problem to
try to assess the presence or absence of
Consciousness in language models even
though many people are interested in
that uh we think that we have more hope
of making progress in the near term with
more well defined um cative capacities
or C functions and things that relate to
forms of certain forms of reasoning
variable binding uh Etc um so we our
framework in principle would apply to
things like Consciousness or as you put
awareness generally speaking but uh we
don't really focus on that for examples
the the other quick thing I wanted to
mention is I I seem to remember that the
frame
from Den but again I'm not a denit
scholar was competence without
comprehension um uh which is seems a
little different from competence without
awareness perhaps depending on how you
think of comprehension um and yeah I
think that does have I think it is a
very interesting phrase that it
does um in fact I I have this project
that un published with Chris Bela who I
think you had on the podcast as well um
on semantic competence in language
models where we use that phrase um to
kind of avoid taking its stance on the
kind of messy Murdy question of whether
llms understand language uh which builds
in all sorts of assumption including
about Consciousness actually for some
people like joho um and we focus on a
more restriced notion of competence and
I think our paper here also has that
property that we we operationalize
competence we end up oper
operationalizing competence in terms of
the sets of knowledge of mechanism and
mechanisms that enable a system to
generalize well in a given domain
basically and in a way that's I suppose
fairly deflationary compared to some
more
expensive understandings of competence
that are related to comprehension or
understanding more broadly but I'll let
you take back
Charles no yeah that was that was good
um the phrase yeah the distinction that
Den draws is between competence with
comprehension and without and I think um
competence with comprehension is the
ability not just to pursue a strategy
that's successful for solving a problem
but to um articulate the strategy in
such a way that you could teach it for
example and
um humans only
sometimes have competence with
comprehension we have many
competences that lack comprehension
right um you know when we learn to walk
for example um we have an amazing
competence that we still can't quite
translate into
robotics because we don't fully
understand how it
works uh and when it comes to large
language models I
think we should
not
expect uh comprehension I mean they have
a an amazing Suite of competences if you
thought that they also had comprehension
then I suppose you would think like well
if you want to understand how a large
language model works you can just ask it
but that's that's a bad strategy nobody
nobody thinks that's a good way to find
out um how a large language model works
so so they're on the um competence
without comprehension side of things
um and in order to figure
out
what in order to figure out what the
mechanisms are that enable its
competencies we have to pursue
strategies that are broadly similar to
the strategies we using you know
cognitive psychology or cognitive
Linguistics um and you know we have to
run experiments so I think that that's
all very compatible with Dan's way of
looking at things um one other thing
I'll
mention um Dan's so so Dan was
uh quite influential to me and we
actually wrote A Commentary
together which pushes back a little bit
on a simple understanding of this
distinction so we were looking at um the
evolution of
metacognition and basically what we
argue is that um given
the gradualism of evolution there must
have been something in between base
level cognition and metacognition so we
shouldn't see that distinction as black
and white and um you know I think that
if you want to contrast the sort
of uh cognitive prowess of
um
a human adult with lots of linguistic
and
scientific uh Concepts at her
disposal with you know a non-human
animal then this strong distinction
between competence with and without
comprehension is reasonable um but in
the space of all possible Minds we
should be open to the view that there
can be you know semic
competent um forms of
cognition and just follow Qui on this uh
it occur to me while I was listening to
you as well that um the first example of
auxilary practice we give auxilary test
demands and specifically the Hugh and
Frank example is a nice is a nice
example where in order to give the metal
linguistic judgment correctly succeed at
that you would need confidence with
comprehension because you need to
understand not only be able to to to to
agree the verb with the subject but know
the rule and know how to formulate it
perhaps reize it uh
for example to teach someone right and
so uh and so when you find that the LM
can do well at the low Tas demand
version of the task and of the high test
the explicit metalinguistic judgments in
some way that's an example of the having
confidence with compion
yeah yeah
nice awesome okay upcycle Club wrote
question given that llms inherently
reflect SCT anthropocentric biases due
to their training on human data and
goals how can we ensure that their
Intermodal discourse aligns with
Humanity's
values
um so the they're inter what discourse
sorry the inter model discourse perhaps
amongst the
models I see I see like in that
Farmville paper
yeah the small the yeah generative
agents yeah the small on
yeah I I think that's beyond the scope
of this paper to be honest but
um I mean we could mute about it yeah
but I don't know that we have I don't
know if this project has much I mean I
think we both have an interest in the
alignment problem uh independently of
this project but I don't think this
project has much to say really about
this I don't know CH what you think uh
yeah yeah and I
don't yeah I don't have anything super
concrete on that okay Dave asks an
example of inserting noise into llm
training that was the section about the
extra tokens do you see any analog to
intermittent reforced to uncertainty
tolerance
because you mentioned the extra tokens
in the Chain of Thought and how that
could also be replaced by by dot dot dot
dot dot and so like what is that telling
us about model
training when um it seems like there's
some situations where adding Superfluous
tokens would diminish signal in data
sets but then here are other situations
where it seems to actually
help um
um yeah so in that particular paper I
think it's called thinking dot by Dot
and there is a sub title um it's by Will
Mar Jacob I think um in that paper um if
I correctly what they did is that
they they introduced just this
one F token it's one meanless token just
a just a
DOT and
train the model to give an answer after
producing a certain number of
dots that's not just like introducing
random gibberish in your training data
it's actually quite a specific
intervention that forces the model to um
learn to perform certain computations
before giving an answer um so so it
makes sense to me that this couldn't
diminish performance and you could get
benefit from that it's not quite the
same as just having that training data
right um just because the token seems
meaningless it's a f token it's a DOT um
it's not just random gibra is just going
to throw off the model and and impede
its its uh the optimization of its
learning function or or this good
Downstream performance um but what it's
going to do is going to force the model
to learn that when there is a DOT token
it can allocate computation with his
attention head and other parts of the
architecture in such a way that it's um
getting
towards deriving the correct token when
it's finally producing the token that
matters and that's meaningful after the
series of thoughts um yeah I don't know
Charles if you have another anwers now
yeah I mean I mean I think it's an
important question because a
priori uh if someone said look we're g
to upend and prepend a whole bunch of
meaningless symbols to an llm input you
might very well think that this will
just weaken the signal to noise ratio
and degrade model
performance so it's against
that background that the empirical
result that it doesn't degrade model
performance um ought to be regarded as a
important clue about how the model Works
um so so so I think that the the
intuition behind this question is indeed
part of the interpretation of the
empirical results right it's it's
surprising for exactly this reason and
then um the theory that's supposed to uh
you know well this is an active
inference podcast right so the theory
that's supposed to help rid some of the
surprise here is um the idea
that given the uh architecture of a
transformer where
it's it has to go through all the tokens
in every cycle um having these extra
tokens
gives it uh sort of more computational
bandwidth and therefore more
expressivity or more capacity to uh you
know locate uh the right spot and
parameter space and and even that in a
way reminds me of let's so so it's not
just that dots improve performance it's
not it's that it was like you mentioned
it was trained to have that and
similarly it it could have been trained
maybe hypothetically to just output
Shakespeare quotes verbatim while you're
processing so that's kind of like a
filler or more of like a sort of that
was a great question it's like these are
linguistic
paddings that that do create time to to
get to the meet so not only does it
signal and
signpost if it's being trained to to
have that meaning which then questions
like so then was it a meaningless dot if
it if if it had a um a cognitive or even
like a a
semantic um aspect I had a question how
do you feel like in
this era Cambrian explosion of diverse
intelligences how can we understand
capacities when they seem so conditional
upon the setting and how the system of
Interest is interacted with like what
are the practical
implications for people who are studying
llms and other synthetic intelligences
from like a safety or reliability or
performance
perspective you want
to no I was throwing it to
you so so so just want make sure the
question so the question is
um
how the how is the notion of a
capacity um changing when we have such
different systems that seem to have
intelligent Behavior yeah and it's so
dependent upon
potentially initially
unintuitive ways of interacting so H how
how can we understand the the
reliability and the performance and the
capacity
of of a
model other than for example by
exhaustively inputting prompts which can
really happen what what could we really
say or
no Andor just how do you feel that this
work re-enters into the ways that people
practically are using the
models right okay yeah uh it's a very
interesting question so the first part
of the question is I think you know part
of the background assumption from for
this paper that I've explicitly defended
in other work is that behavioral
evidence is simply not sufficient in
most cases to arbitrate disputes about
capacities of
LMS um when it comes to human
cognition we do have to rely a lot on on
psychological experiments that are
ultimately behavioral and we do also r
on self reports in a little more than we
can when it comes to alabs because
we despite the move away from relying on
intuition and introspection in the
history of psychology it still has a
role to play but with by and large
probity towards by behavioral
experiments that get increasingly
sophisticated um to re try to regress
engineer what's going on inside the
black box when it comes to LM um
LMS partly because they're so different
from us um relying exclusively on
behavior is even more is even more
difficult because we have even less of
an idea of what might be going on inside
the black box and whether it's anything
like what's going inside our blackbox
and we have reasons to think in fact it
might be very different
so I think I think we both agree that we
have to supplement this with
mechanistic work that essentially
involve performing causal interventions
on the inner mechanisms on the inner
workings of the systems so
decoding representation and computations
that the systems uh that are in
principle available to the systems and
then intervening on them to confirm
hypotheses about Cal role of these
representations and computations and we
have methods to do that in
partly why why we can be a little
optimistic about this project even
though it's it's it's extremely
challenging especially to be scaled up
to large models is because unlike what's
happening in your Cent the brain where
the range of decoding methods and
intervention methods we had is extremely
limited but for ethical and for
simply um practical reasons we don't
just don't have ground trth access to
activations in neurons at least that
easily and we also are generally enabled
to make specific interventions on
activations in the brain uh when it
comes to alms we have full ground truth
knowledge of all activations of every
single part of the network and we also
have full access to all of it for interv
at inference time so that that opens up
a whole new range of things we can do
and that enables us to go beyond
Behavioral Studies and actually decode
these features and circuits or as
researchers put it in the literature or
as philosophers would generally put it
uh representations and computations that
the system is actually making use of and
try to reverse engineer what kind of
what kind of algorithms it's it's making
use of so part of the broader problem
projects that we have with Charles is
to um suppose we start with the investig
investigative kinds as we put as as alib
calls this human C
capacities um we can operationalize them
and do behavioral experiment from the
top down and then from the bottom up we
can also try to reverse engineer the
mechanic building blocks of the
computations and representations that
LMS make use of to solve the task
related to that particular capacity T
and then we can meet somewhere in the
middle and try to uh from that line of
work that approaches things from above
ends um bring to the four some kinds of
mid-level abstractions as we call it or
computational building blocks that might
be key to um the performance of the
system in that domain so for example if
you're interested in the capacity for
reasoning you can start with this very
broad humancentric notion of reason
reasoning then try to operationalize it
in a reasoning task then do some
behavioral testing and then mechanic
interpretability on that reasoning task
find out how the system is solving it
find out how the LM is doing well and
why reverse engineer building blocks
that might for example have to viable
manipulation viable binding and then
from there you might be able to
iteratively refine the notion of
reasoning you started with uh to have a
more specific and per less human C
notion that is now operationalized in
more
lowlevel um More Level terms like uh you
know that that that involve the
manipulation of variables in certain
ways and the Banning of variables to
figures Etc um so yeah so that's I think
the general approach we take now how
that does that does any of that Feit
back into interactions how we humans
interact with LMS I think perhaps one
way in which it could feedback is
simply um in terms of challenging or our
um spontaneous anthropomorphic attitudes
TOS uh to some extent the same way if
you read a lot about Ang cognition
perhaps you will interact with your cat
in a slightly different way uh that you
might maybe not rush the conclusion that
uh when your cat performs a certain
Behavior it has understood what you
think and it's modeling what you're
thinking about what it's thinking or
something um perhaps you
might um adopt a more deflationary
attitude to uh explain the behavior of
your cat doesn't mean you have to love
them any less or doesn't mean you have
to uh um you know if there is the other
thing like if you want at the end of the
day to speak to your cat like a human
because you the r Gman for that then
that's you know all the more part to you
and the same way if you find it useful
to treat llms in the way you interact
with them um to to have F interactions
with them to treat them as if they had
beliefs designes Etc Al of human like
capacities then that's fine if that's
for actual purposes but at least if that
line of work that we are kind of
sketching here ends up maturing enough
the hope is that we can interact with
LMS perhaps in a way that's um where
even if we if we have that kind of
intentional stance and make believe
about what the kind capacities they have
at the background we will know that uh
what their limitations are and what
their actual capacities are I don't know
if you agree with that Charles because
we didn't discuss that much yeah yeah no
I agree with all that I just had a
slightly different um first reaction to
the question I took the question to be
in part about how to deal with the sort
of prompt sensitivity of models the fact
that sometimes we you know write
something that seems natural to us but
provokes an unexpected response from a
large language model and how do we think
about that
um and and the first thought that
occurred to me was just that um we
should distinguish
between different kinds of large
language models um you know we have the
sort of uh huge large language models
which are
um fine-tuned to interact with us in a
particular way and are and here's the
central point they're trained on a a
sort of unthinkably large database
whereas um there are other sorts of
large language models where the training
data is more circumscribed and where we
know uh in more detail you know what um
where you can survey uh what the
training data says and I think if you're
interested in you know what the
mechanisms are underlying the responses
um it's certainly very helpful to uh
look at smaller but nevertheless large
language models where the training data
is known to us because um you know when
you train a model on the entire internet
there are going to be all kinds of uh
you know subtle signals in there that we
don't have much hope of tracing back to
their Source but which will influence
the Model Behavior in all sorts of ways
um but working with these somewhat more
conscripted uh models uh gets rid of
that problem at least in
part cool well where where do you
see the work going or where do you plan
to continue this
direction yeah so we actually so we
wrote this paper this short paper for uh
the icml machine learning conference
International confence machine learning
um that's happening this week in Vienna
and we'll be um getting to Vienna at the
end of the week for the particular
workshop at which we're presenting this
uh paper which is a workshop on language
models and cognitive science
um so there is a very strict page limit
for the
ZL contribution which is four pages but
what we want to do next is to um expand
this into a
more philosophically substantive paper
that's going to be a bit longer um and
that's going to expand on the more
philosophically mey parts of that of
that project um because everything is a
bit compressed in that version that
we're presenting on HML so yeah that's
the next step for us this is a really
useful way first to force ourselves to
write things down after running the Box
piece we wanted to write an academic
piece now we've
written kind of the condens skeleton of
the piece that focuses more that c
caters more to an ml audience and now
the next step is to write the full
philosophy paper or at least that part
of the project to be complete I don't
have to that people have ideas
yeah
yeah I got nothing to add to that
cool yeah it's well it's very
interesting work I think it it brings a
lot of pieces together and it's some
philosophy and cognitive science jumping
in jumping into the the Heat and into
the the spotlight and the relevance and
so it's going to be an exciting Learning
Journey thanks for having us yes yeah
thank you very much cool enjoyable
conversation till next time thank
you
bye e